Hey everyone, if I had to choose just one topic that makes all of the others in
大家好 有一个知识点
linear algebra start to click and which too often
它虽然能统合线性代数的其它知识点
goes unlearned the first time a student takes linear algebra,
但却容易被线性代数的初学者所忽略
it will be this one.
那就是这个知识点
The idea of a linear transformation,
线性变换的概念
and its relation to matrices.
及其与矩阵的关系
For this video, I'm just going to focus on what
本视频将重点讲解
these transformations look like in the case of two dimensions,
二维线性变换
and how they relate to the idea of matrix-vector multiplication.
及其与矩阵-向量乘法的关系
In particular, I want to show you a way to think about matrix-vector multiplication,
具体来讲 我想介绍一种矩阵与向量相乘的思路
that doesn't rely on memorization.
这种思路不用死记硬背
To start, let's just parse this term, linear transformation.
首先 我们先来解释线性变换这个术语
Transformation is essentially a fancy word for function,
变换其实是函数好听点的说法
it's something that takes in inputs,
本质上就是一种接受输入
and spits out an output for each one Specifically in the context of linear algebra,
并输出相应结果的事物 具体来讲 在线性代数中
we like to think about transformations that take in some vector,
变换就是要接受某个矢量
and spit out another vector.
然后输出另一个矢量
So, why use the word transformation instead of function,
既然这两者是同一种事物
if they mean the same thing?
那为什么我们不说 “函数” 而要说 “变换” 呢？
Well, it's to be suggestive of a certain way to visualize this input-output relation.
这是因为 “变换” 一词更直观地体现了输入与输出之间的关系
A great way to understand functions of vectors,
向量函数
is to use movement.
最好借助运动来理解
If a transformation takes some input vector,
变换接受一些输入向量
to some output vector,
并输出相应输出向量的过程
we imagine that input vector moving over to the output vector.
可以想象为输入向量朝输出向量移动的过程
Then to understand the transformation as a whole,
而要将变换作为整体来理解
we might imagine watching every possible input vector,
我们可以想象所有可能输入向量
move over to its corresponding output vector.
朝相应的输出向量移动的场景
It gets really crowded to think about all of the vectors,
要把向量看作箭头
all at once, each one has an arrow.
同时想象所有向量 可能会很乱
So, as I mentioned in the last video,
所以 正如我在上个视频提到的
a nice trick is to conceptualize each vector not as an arrow,
我们可以不把向量看作一个个箭头
but as a single point.
而是当成一个个点
The point where it's tip sets That way,
每个点对应每个向量头部所在的位置
to think about a transformation taking every possible input vector to some output vector,
这样一来 要研究任意可能输入向量移动到相应输出向量的变换过程
we watch every point in space moving to some other point.
就可以想象空间各点移动到另一个点所处位置的场景
In the case of transformations in two dimensions,
二维变换中
to get a better feel for the whole shape of the transformation,
要更好地理解变换的整体形状
I like to do this with all of the points on an infinite grid.
我个人喜欢想象无限网格上各点做运动的场景
I also sometimes like to keep a copy of the grid in the background,
有时候我还会将原始网格保留在背景里
just to help keep track of where everything ends up,
以便作为点运动起点
relative to where it starts.
和终点的参照
The effect for various transformations moving around all of the points in space is,
不同变换移动空间各点的效果
and you've got to admit, beautiful.
不得不承认 很漂亮
It gives the feeling of squishing,
看起来像是在压缩
and morphing space itself.
和扭曲空间本身
As you can imagine though arbitrary transformations can look pretty complicated.
你应该不难想象 自由变换看起来可能会很复杂
But luckily, linear algebra limits itself to a special type of transformation.
好在线性代数涉及的变换很特殊
Ones that are easier to understand, called linear transformations.
很容易理解 我们称之为线性变换
Visually speaking, a transformation is linear if it has two properties.
从几何的角度讲 线性变换需要满足两个特点
All lines must remain lines without getting curved,
所有线都必须是直线 不能弯曲
and the origin must remain fixed in place.
原点必须固定不动
For example, this right here would not be a linear transformation,
比如 这个肯定不是线性变换
since the lines get all curvy.
因为所有线都弯曲了
And this one right here although it keeps the line straight,
这个虽然都是直线
is not a linear transformation,
但也不是线性变换
because it moves the origin.
因为原点位置发生了变化
This one here fixes the origin,
这个原点位置不变
and it might look like it keeps lines straight,
线看起来也没有弯曲
but that's just because I'm only showing the horizontal,
但这是因为你只看到了网格的横线
and vertical grid lines.
和纵线
When you see what it does to a diagonal line,
如果你观察斜线
it becomes clear that it's not at all linear,
就会发现这并不全是线性的
since it turns that line all curvy.
斜线发生了扭曲
In general, you should think of linear transformations as
总地来说 线性变换时
keeping grid lines parallel, and evenly spaced.
网格线应保持平行且等距分布
Some linear transformations are simple to think about,
有些线性变换很容易想象
like rotations about the origin.
比如围绕原点进行旋转
Others are a little trickier to describe with words.
也有些比较复杂 很难用语言描述